This is my kitchen table and also my
filing system.
Over much of the past three decades,
I've been an investor the highest
calling of mankind I've often thought
was private equity.
And then I started interviewing.
I watch your interviews, Coach.
I know how to do something.
I've learned in doing my interviews how
leaders make it to the top.
I asked him how much you wanted.
He said to 50.
I said, Fine.
I didn't negotiate with him.
I didn't know due diligence.
I have something I'd like to sell and
how they stay there.
You don't feel inadequate now because
being only the second wealthiest man in
the world, Is that right?
In the long history of the British
government, only one woman has served as
Chancellor of the Exchequer.
In effect, the Secretary of the Treasury
of the British government.
That woman is Rachel Reeves.
Had a chance at Davos recently to sit
down with Rachel Reeves and talk about
her role as Chancellor of the Exchequer
and the British economy.
In your position, Chancellor of the
Exchequer, you are the equivalent of the
United States or the Secretary of
Treasury?
Yes, but also the head of the Office of
Management and Budget.
Do you not prepare the budget for the
the government?
I do.
I do also prepare the the budget.
We have an independent forecaster who
provides the forecast and costs the
policies that we put forward.
But what is in the budget is my choice.
The policies that I put forward.
And we have an annual budget.
I delivered the last of my budgets in
November last year.
And in England, you have to balance the
budget.
Or you can borrow money.
You can borrow money, but we're reducing
that.
I don't think that it is
good fiscal or economic policy to just
constantly borrow, especially to pay for
day to day spending.
And for the last few years, like many
countries, including the US, we've been
running a budget deficit of around 5% of
GDP.
We are now bringing that down steadily.
It will be just over 4% I think, this
year, then falling to about three and a
half percent.
We've got the fastest rate of fiscal
consolidation going on in the UK of any
country in the G7.
Our debt burden as a share of GDP is
not too far of 100%.
I want to bring that down.
I also want to bring down the cost of
servicing that debt because at the
moment one in £10 of everything
government spends is actually on debt
interest.
And so reducing government borrowing
costs, which we managed to achieve last
year and reducing the debt burden as a
share of GDP.
Two important priorities for me.
In the budget you have proposed, you
proposed a tax increase.
Is that very popular to doing?
Will you get it approved because you
control the parliament?
We do have a big majority in Parliament.
When I became chancellor, I inherited a
bit of a mess, a bit of a mess fiscally
and in terms of economic performance and
the cost of living.
And the previous government had made a
number of spending commitments without
saying where the money was going to come
from.
And what is called the reserve, which is
set aside for emergencies, had been
spent three or four times over.
Just three months into the financial
year.
I had to put that right.
And that required a number of
adjustments both on spending and indeed
on tax.
When you come in as a business leader
and you're taking on a business that has
not been working well, that is not
living within its means, does not have a
clear plan.
You have to sort it out.
And I to fix that mess now and be able
to pursue my plans, my plans for growth
and to ease the cost of living
challenges.
But that did require quite a big repair
job to put the public finances on a
solid footing again.
As we look in this calendar year.
Do you think the UK will grow at two or
3% or so?
What kind of projections are you for?
GDP growth?
Real GDP growth expected to be around
one and a half percent, obviously
nominal.
That would be around three and a half
percent
a year.
I want growth to be faster than that
last year.
I think we'll come out as the second
fastest growing economy in the G7 when
all the numbers are totted up.
But none of the economies in the G7 are
growing as fast as we could, as fast as
I think our potential is.
And that's why, as the government growth
is our number one priority for the Prime
Minister, Keir Starmer and myself and
our industrial strategy backing sectors
like AI and tech, clean energy, life
sciences and our defence sectors focus
on stability to bring down interest
rates and inflation investment both
public and private in infrastructure,
including ambitious plans for Oxford and
Cambridge and also in the north of
England.
And then
deregulation, reforming our planning
system to make it easier to get things
done in Britain.
I think we'll start seeing the benefits
of that pay off this year.
Now, many wealthy people who are not
British by birth who've moved to England
in recent years, maybe to avoid their
local countries taxes have found that
recently the non-dom taxes have
increased dramatically in the UK and
they have left the UK.
Is that been a problem having wealthy
people leave the UK or it's not a big
problem.
We want Britain to be a magnet for, you
know, wealth and talent entrepreneurs
from around the world.
We did have quite an anachronistic
system that if your father was born
abroad you could claim a non domicile
for tax purposes in the UK.
That wasn't fair.
It's not a rule that any other country
has.
And so the previous government and now
this government have got rid of that.
We also made some changes around trusts
and inheritance tax, although in the
budget just in November we relaxed some
of those rules so that for a flat fee.
That you could take trusts out of your
inheritance tax.
So we have listened to feedback from
wealthy individuals who perhaps want to
make Britain that home or have already
made Britain that home.
We've also introduced a very generous
scheme for people coming to the UK and
wanting to bring foreign income and
gains to the UK.
Previously they were taxed at normal
rates of of of income tax.
We have reduced that to try and
encourage people to bring not just
themselves in their talent but their
wealth to the UK.
Britain is an open trading economy and
we have to be to be successful, open to
business, open to investment, open to
trade and open to talent.
Now the world has seen enormous amounts
of growth in the technology space,
particularly AI.
And you've mentioned Quantum is also
coming along.
But as you look back over the last
couple of years,
if you grow up in the UK or the EU, you
don't really rely to get through the day
on European built technologies.
The technologies are often the ones that
people use are built in the United
States.
Why do you think that the entrepreneurs
in the UK and the EU haven't yet built
technologies that the whole world says
we need that technology, we need to have
our Facebook or our Google product or
something like that?
Is there any inherent reason you think
it is or just been bad luck for the last
X number of years?
Well, I think that's a really good
challenge.
And your amazing tech companies like
Google and Facebook and Apple, etc., we
don't have one of those in the UK or
indeed in Europe.
We're very good at adopting new
technologies in the UK and that spurs
productivity growth, which is beginning
to pick up now in the UK.
But we've also got some really exciting
businesses on the frontier of new
technologies like
quantum and digital processing.
So I think there are some exciting
opportunities.
And one of the things that we want to do
with Oxford, Cambridge is to create a
big link between those two universities,
the 60 or 70 miles apart.
But there's no direct train link between
them.
There are some great towns and cities on
that route between those two cities.
We want to bring them together and
create, you know, our version, a British
version of Silicon Valley in the UK,
where we can really capture the
creativity and the imagination of
British founders and help them grow
their businesses here.
One of the challenges have had in the UK
for loads of startups, but as I scale up
the drift towards America, the reforms
we're making, particularly pension
reforms to unlock long term patient
capital to venture capital to private
equity in the UK that is really
exciting, will keep more of those
businesses here.
We put in a load of tax incentives as
well in the budget to back founders and
entrepreneurs, and we're increasing the
tax incentives to stay listed in the UK.
So we're doing some exciting things.
I do think that that will reap dividends
too.
Now in the United States, there's been a
well-publicised feud between the
president of the United States and the
chairman of the Federal Reserve Board,
and in effect, the President is saying I
should have more influence on what
interest rates are.
Would it ever occur to the Chancellor of
the Exchequer to tell the head of the
Bank of England lower interest rates or
leaders don't do that in this country?
No.
Since 1997, naturally, the previous
Labour chancellor, Gordon Brown, granted
operational independence to the Bank of
England.
It's parliament that sets the inflation
target.
That's 2% for the UK, and then the bank
have the tools of interest rates to meet
that target.
Now, you know, I worked at the Bank of
England and I
have huge respect for that institution
and believe that the way that we have
good policymaking is to take the
politics out of interest rate decisions.
And I think that serves the UK economy
well.
We set fiscal policy as a government and
then the Bank of England set monetary
policy.
And I think the operational independence
for central banks is one of the things
that preserves stability and gives
confidence to people to invest.
Now ten former Chancellor of the
Exchequer became prime minister,
including Winston Churchill, among
others.
So if you ever thought about the
possibility that you might follow in
their path and be the first woman to be
Chancellor of the Exchequer and then
Prime Minister,
I know that politicians often say, I
don't want to do that job.
I really don't want to do that job.
The job that I've always wanted to do in
politics is to be Chancellor of the
Exchequer before I became an MP.
I worked in banking and financial
services and started my career as an
economist at the Bank of England.
For me, being chancellor is my absolute
dream job and it's the only job I want
in politics.
Let's talk a bit about your background.
Where did you grow up?
I grew up in Lewisham, in south east
London.
My mum and dad were primary school
teachers.
I went to my local state school and it
was when I was at school that I got
involved in politics.
And the reason being when I was at
secondary school, our sixth form where
we did our final exams was a couple of
prefabricated huts in the playground,
which was basically freezing cold in the
winter or baking hot in the summer.
Our school library was turned into a
classroom because there were more
students and there was space and there
were never enough textbooks to go
around.
And I felt very strongly that the
governments that we had then in the
1980s and 1990s in the UK, conservative
governments didn't care very much about
schools like mine, the community in
which I grew up, and I wanted to do
something about it.
And at the time the leader of the Labour
Party, the opposition party at the time
was Tony Blair, and I heard him say that
his three priorities were education,
education, education.
And that really resonated with me
because I believe the talent is equally
distributed.
But opportunity isn't.
But education can give everybody the
opportunities that they deserve to
fulfil their potential.
And so that's why I got involved in
politics and why I got involved in the
Labour Party.
And did you go to college?
Yeah, I was the third person at my
school to go to Oxford University.
It wasn't a traditional route for people
from my school to go to university at
all, let alone to a university like
Oxford.
But I remember two years before I
applied to go to Oxford, my head at
school giving an assembly and said,
Today two girls from our school are in
Oxford doing an interview to go to the
university there, and we should all keep
our fingers crossed for them all day
because it would be an amazing
achievement for our school.
And I thought, Wow, I've never thought
about something like that, but I'm one
of the top performing girls in my year.
Perhaps in a couple of years time, that
might be something I could do.
And it just so decide in my mind that
that was a possibility for someone like
me and for a girl from the school like I
was at.
And so two years later, I did put in my
application and I got a place to read
Philosophy, Politics and Economics at
Oxford University.
I later went on to do a masters degree
in Economics at the London School of
Economics.
So I've been very blessed to have a very
good education from some of the best
universities and colleges in the UK.
After you got that education, did you
sort of take a job at the Bank of
England?
Is that what you did?
Yes.
Yeah, my, my macroeconomics tutor at
Oxford, he said the Bank of England was
a finishing school for economists and I
thought, Yeah, that sounds like what I
would like to do.
And so I had an offer from an investment
bank and I had an offer from the Bank of
England, and I chose the Bank of England
because I wanted to be a proper
economist.
And, and also I've always strongly
believed in public service and so were
working for the Bank of England was a
great job for me as my first job after
university.
And how long were you there?
I was there for just under six years.
I in fact, actually, whilst I was there
as well, I had a brief secondment to
Washington where I worked at the British
Embassy as the second economic
Secretary, and that was in 2002, 2003.
So again, a time of huge volatility in
the world Not long after 911 when the UK
and the US went to war in Iraq.
And so it was a fascinating time to be
in Washington.
And I was reporting back to the UK
Treasury and to the bank and liaising
with the the the US economic team as
well.
So after you finish that tour of duty,
you ultimately decided to run for
parliament?
Yes, I went and worked in the private
sector for a bit.
I worked for Halifax, Bank of Scotland,
which is now part of Lloyds Banking
Group.
I worked in retail banking, which is
what took me to Leeds, where I'm now a
member of Parliament.
But did you in the first time you ran?
No, no, no.
The third time actually, that I ran, I
ran in what is traditionally a.
A conservative seat in the south of
England in Bromley, which is close to
where I grew up.
But then I got this job up in Yorkshire,
moved up there.
A safer seat became available and and I
stood there.
Okay, so after you ran the first time
and didn't win and the second time you
didn't win, you didn't say maybe
politics was not for me?
No.
The first time I did, it was sort of
like it was like for me, it was the
first time I had done anything publicly
political.
I'd always been alone to my local branch
meetings of my party.
I'd gone along to Labour Party
conference, but I'd never had a sort of
public platform for my politics.
And I thought, Well, I'll give it a go.
I'll see what it's like and see if it's
something that I would like to do in the
in the longer term.
So I was very I was young when I first
stood for Parliament.
I think I was about 26 and then the
following year, sadly, the MP I stood
against, he died suddenly.
And so there was a by election and so I
stood again for my party.
But it was 2010 that I first got elected
to Parliament.
So it was 250 years ago that my country
issued a Declaration of Independence and
said to your country, we're breaking
away.
Do you think if the British government
had said, look, forget the taxes we're
imposing, let's be friends, the UK would
still be part of the United States or
the U.S.
would be still part of UK, and would
that make the world a better place Or or
you're happy with what happens?
I'm not going to go back 250 years and
try and rewrite that period of history.
But I am really proud of the strong
ties, the cultural ties, the family
ties, the business ties, the military
and intelligence ties between our
country.
There's no greater partnership in the
world than that between the UK, UK and
the US.
And that's been true under different
prime ministers, different presidents.
We've got a very strong relationship
between my Prime Minister Keir Starmer
and your President, Donald Trump.
I think that serves both of our
countries well.
Does it mean we're always going to agree
on everything?
And that's the thing about the closest
of friends.
Don't always have to agree on
everything.
You can exchange views and that is a
healthy thing to do.
But recognising that, you know, what
binds us together was so much stronger
for foreign investors.
People who live in the United States or
in China or Asia.
Why should they invest their money in
the UK?
This is an exciting time.
You think about all of the growth
sectors in the economy today and those
are all areas where Britain has real
advantages, real strengths.
You.
In the US, we have an aging population
and without immigration very much now
our population is aging much more than
it has in the past.
Does the UK have an ageing population
issue as well or not?
Yes, we do.
I don't think it is stark, as in some
other countries.
I think that the immigration policy is a
challenge for all Western countries to
get that balance right.
And in Britain we are building an
immigration system and a visa system
that is going to be all about and is all
about attracting the best talent into
the UK because it's not just a numbers
game.
It's the quality of the the workforce
that you're bringing into the UK.
And we believe if you're attracting the
top, top academics and researchers, the
top entrepreneurs, the people who went
to the best universities in the world,
you're not displacing jobs.
What you're doing is creating more
wealth and opportunity.
And so, you know, we're doing a number
of visa waivers for fee waivers for the
top talent in the world to come to the
UK.
And we want to send out the message loud
and clear that Britain wants to be a
magnet for the best talent in the world
when respect to the economy here.
Is it your view that the UK economy is
going to grow somewhat like the EU
economy?
You're not going to outgrow the UK?
We are.
We are, if you will.
Last year we outgrew Italy, France and
Germany and I think that will continue
to be the same this year.
You know, we are an open trading
economy.
Trade deals with emerging markets around
the world.
The best trade deal with the US.
We've got great innovation going on
through our universities and with our
entrepreneurs and founders in the in the
UK.
We are a services based economy, but
also with amazing advanced manufacturing
as well.
So I think we are set up for success in
the UK for foreign investors, people who
live in the United States or on the
continent in Europe or in China or Asia.
Why should they invest their money in
the UK?
Is the growth rate good enough to
attract capital?
Are the regulations fair enough and easy
enough?
Why should somebody invest in the UK?
Well, the UK stock market was one of the
best performing stock markets in the
world last year.
The Footsie 100 went up by just over
21%.
So pretty good returns on your
investment.
We have got in the UK four of the top
universities in the world with some
amazing businesses spinning out of those
universities in life sciences and
quantum, in AI, increasingly in the
defence sector and dual use
technologies.
So tons of exciting stuff happening in
the UK.
We've got some amazing unicorn
businesses have started and are now
scaling up in the UK and we're making it
easier for businesses to list and to
raise finance in Britain.
So this is an exciting time.
You think about all of the growth
sectors in the economy today and those
are all areas where Britain has real
advantages, real strengths.
And so that's why I think this is going
to be Britain's year.
I'm really confident.
So what do you do in your spare time?
I assume you can't be Chancellor of the
Exchequer 24 hours a day, seven days a
week.
Are you an athlete?
You collect anything?
Do you have any hobbies?
What do you do on the outside?
Well, I've got two children who are aged
12 and ten, so they keep me pretty busy
when I'm not working and I love spending
time with them.
I had a wonderful time over Christmas
and New Year where I got to indulge in a
bit more cooking, which I don't have
time for very much with the usual cut
and thrust of work and politics.
Also a keen runner and try and go
running several times a week.
And very lucky, very blessed in London
to live near the beautiful royal parks
in London.
And so make use of running through
those.
If you're running in the park, do people
come up to you and say lower taxes or
anything like that?
Is that ever happened?
I try and go running quite early in the
morning to avoid that sort of thing and
keep my head down.
And your children call you Chancellor or
they just call you Mom.
I've been mum is about the politest
thing they call me
now.
They're wonderful children and they
absolutely keep me grounded.
They've got very strong views and very
strong principles already themselves.
I'm incredibly proud of that.
Final question is I've often thought the
best titles in the world for a job you
can have are Supreme Allied Commander,
president of the World Bank, Chief
Justice of the United States and
Chancellor of the Exchequer.
So do your friends call you Rachael?
They call you now, Chancellor.
Ms.
Exchequer, What are your friends call
you now?
They are Chancellor of the Exchequer.
I'm just still Rachel to them.
But the other day I bumped into the head
of MI6, our security service, and I was
with my 12 year old and I said, you
know, this woman is the head of MI6, our
security service.
And my daughter said, that is a much
cooler job with my moms.
So I was certainly put in my place to.